Central New York Trade Catalogs and Business Ephemera
Central New York Trade Catalogs and Business Ephemera
1816-1962
1865-1900
Special Collections Research Center
2 linear ft.
Collection of catalogs, trade cards, merchants' scrip, letterhead, photographs, and other ephemera from businesses in and around Syracuse, New York. Towns represented include Elbridge. Syracuse, Marcellus, Litchfield, Morristown, Scipio, and others. Also includes records and ledgers from some businesses, including L. C. Smith Typewriter (forerunner of Smith-Corona).
2537058
Biographical History
Central New York has been the home of many companies that went on to become known nationwide, among them Smith Bros. Cough Drops, L.C. Smith Typewriter Company (which later became Smith Corona), Oneida Silverware, Clark Music Company and the Franklin Automobile.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Central New York Trade Catalogs and Business Ephemera consists of correspondence, photographs, printed material and miscellany related to businesses and industries in and around Central New York.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is divided alphabetically by type. Larger sections, such as trade catalogs and correspondence, are further ordered alphabetically by company name.
Related Material
See also the
Central New York Local History Collection
and
Central New York Cultural Ephemera
. There are also separate collections for a number of businesses and companies, such as Oneida Silverware (
Oneida Community Collection
), Endicott-Johnson (
Charles F. Johnson
and related collections), and
Clark Music Company
(
Melville Clark
); please refer to under "Business and Industry" or under "New York State" for a full listing.
For full descriptions of the merchants' scrip, see New York State scrip and private issues by Gordon L. Harris (S.l.: G.L. Harris, c2001), call no. New York HG627 .N4 2001 (refer to to locate).
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Business and Industry; Akin, John W.; Chace, A. Frank B.; Evans, Mary Elizabeth.; Osborne family.; Syracuse Cart Company.; Birdsall Engine company.; Candy Kitchen.; Protectall Safes.; Baker Dash Works.; J.R. Clancy.; Perry Seed Store.; Elmwood Stud.; National Banker's Express Company.; American Seating Company.; Boyd's Syracuse Guide.; Business enterprises -- New York (State) -- History.; Commercial catalogs.; Liquor laws -- New York (State); License system -- New York (State); Retail trade -- Law and legislation -- New York (State); Elbridge (N.Y.) -- Commerce.; Syracuse (N.Y.) -- Commerce.; Utica (N.Y.) -- Commerce.; Cayuga County (N.Y.) -- Commerce.; Advertisements.; Advertisements.; Brochures.; Correspondence.; Fliers (printed matter); Letterheads.; Printed ephemera.; Receipts (financial records); Scrip.; Trade cards.; Trade catalogs.; Commercial businesses.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Scrip gift of Gordon L. Harris, July 2003. Other material purchased with funds from the Library Associates.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  Receipts, inquiries, etc. on corporate or business letterhead. Material is in alphabetical order by company name; if company name is a person (for example, "L. C. SMith") it is filed under the surname.
  - Birdsall Engine Co., 1918 (Box 1)
  - Cayuga Chief Manufacturing Company, 1867-1874 (Box 1)
  - Navarino auto garage, journal, correspondence, invoices, receipts (Box 1)
  - L. C. Smith Typewriter Company, 1890-1904; material has been removed and is now part of the L.C. Smith & Bros. Typewriter Co. Collection (Box 1)
  - Businesses, A-H (Box 1)
  - Businesses, I-Z (Box 1)
  - Businesses, unidentified (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous, includes accordion-folded souvenir series of tiny photographs of Dryden, New York; photograph of Vernon Downs; more (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Cazenovia-area checks, 1830-1859 (Box 1)
  - Ephemera
    - Genuine Buckeye Mower and Reaper advertising broadside (Map-case 102)
    - Miscellaneous, fliers, brochures, savings stamps, checks, etc. (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (oversize) (Oversize 1)
  - Maps
    - Cartoon-style map of Syracuse, 1977; shows all major businesses and attractions, by Francesca Profili (Map-case 102)
    - Miscellaneous, map of Syracuse with street directory; maps of lots in Lyncourt Lawns, Lyncourt Knolls, Eastwood; more. (Oversize 1)
  - Merchant's scrip, non-legal-tender currency issued by local merchants (Box 1)
  - Stocks and bonds
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, oversize (Oversize 1)
  - Trade cards, small printed cards intended as advertising
    - Albums, 2 volumes (Oversize 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Trade catalogs
    - Companies, A-M, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Companies, N-Z (Box 3)
    - A-Z, oversize (Oversize 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Elbridge account book, 1869-1871; groceries, dry goods, tobacco, liquor (Box 3)
  - Liquor and wine license applications, Cayuga County, 1933-1934 (Box 3)
  - "Yellow Kid" advertisement, copper block for printing, wood-backed copper plate for printing the advertisement; ad is for an unnamed farm implement company, "THRESHERS, SHELLERS, FEED CUTTERS, PLOWS, &c" (not foldered) (Box 3)
  - Unidentified account book, 1920s[?] (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, Boyd's Syracuse Guide and Street Directory; insurance forms, recipe books, calendars, etc. (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (oversize) (Oversize 1)